十五年前，一个科学实验出了岔子，带来高智慧猿猴物种的         。
期间由猿猴流感衍生出的病毒，几乎摧毁了整个人类族群。
崛
起
凭借凯撒的统领；新猿猴文明          初现，
人类种族的幸存者只能奋力挣扎以求共存。
但因猿族叛徒高巴向人类展开复仇袭击，最终引发了战争。
黎
明
人类向北面军事基地内集结的残余美国陆军发出紧急求救，
冷酷的特种部队上校和他的勇猛营士兵们受令去歼灭猿猴族。
传言指凯撒在逃避追捕的近二年间，
处身于丛林中的秘密指挥基地内组编战斗。
随着          的肆虐…
战
争
之
极
终
：
起
崛
球
猩
》
《
是那条战壕吗？
Is that the trench?
看似里面还有更多猿猴
It looks like there's more of them inside.
E26呼叫指挥
Ehco 2-6 to command.
上校，北面丛林发现三只猿猴
Colonel, we got eyes on three kongs in the north woods
其中一只有武装，我们的猩猩刚发现了另一条战壕
One of them is armed, our donkey just spotted another trench
他们的基地可能就在附近
Maybe their base is near.
是的，长官
Yes, sir.
是，长官。  收到，完毕。
Yes, sir. Copy, over.
你，过来
You! Come here.
牧师！
Preacher!
拿着枪的那一个
The one with the gun.
- 一旦你把它击倒，你们立马占领那战壕     - 是，长官。
- As soon he guns him down, you guys take out the trench.     - Yes sir.
开火！
Fire!
快上！
Come on!
装填弹药！
Reload!
撤退！ 撤退！
Fallback! Fallback!
上校，你听到吗？ 上校？
Colonel, do you copy? Colonel?
- 你是谁     - 我是牧师，长官。 是牧师！
- Who is this?     - Preacher sir. Is Preacher!
士兵你在何处？ 我需要你的位置
Where are you soldier? I need your position.
- 我不知道     - 你能看见什么？
- I don't know.     -  What do you see?
什么也看不清，我们损失惨重，队长亦已阵亡！长官
I can't see anything, sir. We lost a lot of men and captain is dead!  Sir
- 冷静，你现在是指挥官了     - 现由我指挥？
- Calm down. You're in command now.     - Command now?
我认为现在只剩下我一个了
I think it's just me by myself now.
上校，我不认为我能做到，长官
Colonel, I don't think I'm gonna make it, sir.
很抱歉，非常对不起，长官
I'm sorry. I am so sorry, sir.
听我说。  尽你所能杀敌吧
Listen to me, you kill enemy as many as you can.
不，不，不！
No, No, No!
六十三名猿猴阵亡
Sixty-three dead.
就是你了，你是凯撒
You are him. You're Caesar.
我们找你已有段时间了
We've been searching for you for so long.
我们听闻你拥有一个秘密的指挥基地，但我们从来没有找到它
We heard you had a hidden command base, but we could never find it.
我们中某些人认为你可能已经死亡
Some of us were starting to think that you might be dead,
但麦卡洛上校说 你就藏在这里某处
but Colonel McCullough said you were out here somewhere.
- 你这样干会被杀的！     - 停吧！
- You had been kill so way!     - Stop it!
- 什么？     - 牠们是畜牲，会把我们吞掉
- What?     - They're animals. He's gonna swallow us.
我没有挑起这场战争
I did not start this war.
引发战争的猿猴…已死了
The Ape who did... is dead.
他的名字叫高巴
His name was Koba.
我杀了他
I killed him.
- 现在，我只为保护猿猴们而战斗     - 是吗？
- Now, I'm fight only to protect the Apes.     - Yeah?
那他如何？ 我们还有十个以上像他那样
What about him? We got ten more like him.
我认识这些猿猴们，他们追随高巴
I know these Apes. They followed Koba.
他们尝试杀了我
They tried to kill me.
他们害怕我将会怎样对待他们
They fear what I would do to them.
所以现在…
So now...
他们顺从你…
They serve you...
只是为了活命
Just to survive.
我并不怕你！
I don't fear you!
你定是恐惧了！
You must fear!
你认为丛林还能保护你多久？
How long you think woods can protect you?
人类要灭掉你
Humans destroy you.
他们的上校拥有所有的力量
Their Colonel has all power.
对他们来说，他不仅仅是个人类
For them, he is more that just human.
他掌控一切
He's everything.
他说：当凯撒一死
He says, "First Caesar die...
你们全体也命不久矣
then all of you die."
温达！ 带这叛徒出去！
Winter! Take this traitor outside!
这些人类我们怎样处置？
What should we do with the humans?
你放我们走吗？
You let us go?
告诉你们的上校，你们见过我了
Tell your Colonel, You have seen me now.
并且我要给他一个讯息...
And I have a message for him...
「让我们穿越丛林，杀戮将可终止」
"Leave us passed the woods and the killing can stop."
你认为他们会将讯息传递给他吗？
Do you think they will give him the message?
他们本身就是个口讯，莫利斯
They are the message, Morris.
他会明白到我们并非野蛮人
He will see we are not savages.
那叛徒袭击了我！ 他逃走了！
The traitor attacked me! He got away!
高巴仍继续缠扰着我们
Koba still haunts us.
我看不见他会原谅人类对他作出的恶行
I did not seen that he could not forgive what humans did to him.
没人会知道将有何种情度的黑暗
No one could have known how much darkness...
在他心中存在着
...was living inside him.
父亲！
Father!
欢迎回家，华格道
Welcome home, Raketo.
你看似很疲倦
You look tired.
这是个漫长旅程
It was a long journey.
父亲，我们有所发现！
Father, we found something!
来吧
Come.
母亲！
Mother!
科尼利亚斯
Cornelius
给兄长问好！
Say hi to your brother!
看看谁在这，儿子
Look who's here, son...
力克
Lake.
这就是了，父亲
This is it, Father.
我们可以重新开始… 一个新家园
We can start over... A new home.
那些山脉背后有什么东西，儿子？
What is beyond those mountains, son?
给他们看，洛基
Show them, Rocket.
一个沙漠！
A desert!
路途遥远
The journey is long...
但就因为这样，人类才找不到我们
But that is why humans will not find us.
我们需要今晚起程！
We must leave tonight!
今晚？ 这不可能吧！
Tonight? That's impossible!
我们还能等多久，力克？
How long can we wait, Lake?
士兵越来越近了！
Soldiers getting closer!
温达
Winter.
你的儿子一早已离开了，凯撒
Your son's been gone, Caesar.
他根本不知道这里是何等艰苦
He doesn't know how hard it's been.
我知你受惊了
I know you are scared.
我们全体皆是
We all are
但我们仍在计划着…
But we are still planning...
是的，我们必需找出一个安全逃离丛林的方法
Yes. We must to find a safe way out of the woods.
你们两人能力有限
There were only two of you.
但我们人手众多
But we are many.
我们将会找出离开这里的方法
We'll find a way out of here.
猿猴们团结就会强大
Apes together strong.
留在这儿，儿子
Stay here, son.
保护好你的母亲及兄弟！
Protect your mother and brother!
凯撒！ 有何不妥？！
Caesar! What's wrong?!
有多少猿猴在巡逻？
How many on patrol?
五个，或六个
Five? Six?
召集他们！
Get them!
路加，与华格道同去
Luca, go with Raketa.
单位呼叫指挥，上校请答话
Unit calling command, Colonel.
洛基，发生什么事？
Rocket? What happening?
我听到他的通话！ 上校已到这里了！
I heard him talking! The Colonel is here!
我高声宣布，目标已达成。
Loudly I, target acquired.
我高声宣布，目标已达成。 重复，金刚已死
Loudly I, target acquired. Repeat, King Kong is dead.
走吧！ 我将由这里往上撤
Let's go. I'll get up from here.
凯撒
Caesar
我们找不到温达！
We can not find Winter!
他受惊了！ 我怀疑他已背叛了我们！
He was Scared! I think he betrayed us!
你找到了科尼利亚斯吗？
Have you found Cornelius yet?
我们仍在找
We're still searching.
那去找凯撒的小儿子吧
Let's go look for Caesar's little son.
过来，科尼利亚斯
Come, Cornelius.
你现在安全了
You are safe now.
力克
Lake.
你爱我的儿子
You loved my son.
照护他的弟弟，直到我回来
Look after his brother, until I return.
你不与我们一起到新家园去吗？
You're not coming with us to our new home?
不了
No.
跟力克走
Go with Lake.
凯撒！
Caesar!
你不跟他们一起走吗？！
You're not going after them?!
不是他们，要找“他”
Is not them, him.
凯撒，你是我们的领袖！
Caesar, you are our leader!
我们没有你不能离开！
We can't leave without you!
你必定要
You must.
那些士兵很快便会回来
The soldiers will be back soon.
父亲！
Father!
当我找到他后，士兵们将会追捕我
When I find him, the soldiers will come after me.
让我给你们一个好机会，逃出丛林
Let me give you the best chance to get out of the woods.
他要往那里去？！
Where is he going?!
凯撒！ 凯撒！
Caesar! Caesar!
那些军营是经常迁移的
The soldiers' camp is always moving.
我的护卫知道军营在哪里
My guards think they know where it is
让我引领你
Let me take you
你需要我来当你的后援！
You need me to back you up!
不用！
No!
拜托
Please.
我知道失去了儿子的滋味
I know what it's like to lose a son
我或许没能救他回来
I may not make him back.
所以为什么我要跟着来
That's why I'm coming
是为了确保你能达成
To make sure you do.
护卫认为士兵就在这里
Guards think soldiers here.
总是有烟火吹生
Always fires burning.
这里没有人
No one here.
搜索这片区域
Search the area.
我只想将这东西放下
I'll just gonna put this down.
他独个儿在这里干什么？
What's he doing out here alone?
可能他是一名逃兵
Maybe he's a deserter?
四处搜搜
Look around
要什么就拿走吧
Take what you can.
她出了点问题
Something wrong with her.
我不认为她可以正常说话
I do not think he can speak.
来吧
Come
她独自留下来会死的
She'll die out here alone.
我们不能携她同行，莫利斯
We can not take her, Morris.
我明白...
I understand...
但我不能留下她
But I cannot leave her.
你找到上校没有？
Did you find the Colonel?
没找到
No.
温达
Winter.
上校在那里？
Where's the Colonel?
他走了
He's gone.
已走了？
Gone?
他早上走了
He left this morning...
带着大伙人随他同行
...took many men with him
还有更多士兵正由北面下来
More soldiers are coming down from the North.
上校将与他们会合
The Colonel will meet with them...
在边境处
at the border.
在那里干什么？  为何事？
What's do here? Why?
我不知
I do not know.
但余下的我们将会明早起程
But the rest of us are going tomorrow.
猩猩们认为北面的士兵
The donkeys think the soldiers from the North...
是为了协助完成歼灭整个猿猴族而来
...are coming to help finish off the apes for good.
在山上战斗的哪天
That day, after the battle on the hill...
被活捉的猩猩获许诺，上校会留我们一命...
The donkey we caught promised is that the Colonel will spare my life...
如果我肯告诉他们，你的藏身地点。
if I told them where you were hiding.
原谅我！
Forgive me!
我的儿子
My son,
我的妻子
My wife,
都死了
Are dead.
现在我们怎办？
Now what do we do?
等待直至士兵离开
Wait till the soldiers go...
跟着他们就可找到上校
Follow them to the Colonel.
高巴
Koba?
猿猴不会杀害猿猴
Apes do not kill Apes.
士兵开始离开了！
The soldiers are leaving!
他们停下来
They stopped.
他们向什么东西开火射击？
What are they shooting at?
我不知道
I do not know.
为何他们开枪射你？
Why did they shoot you?
和她一样！
Like her!
他也不能说话！
He cannot Speak!
他的伤势会引致他死亡
He will die of those wounds.
路加
Luca.
那些士兵去了哪里？！
Where did the soldiers go ?!
温达说他们向边境方向去了
Winter said they were going to the border.
是的，但确实方向在哪儿？！
Yes, but which way is that?!
坏...猿猴
Bad... Ape.
坏猿猴
Bad Ape.
你是谁？
Who are you?
你在这里干什么？
What are you doing here?
我不认为他明白
I do not think he understands.
我不认识他
I don't recongnize him
他不是我们族群的一份子
He's not one of us.
你是否在这里孤身独处？
Are you alone here?
好冷
Cold?
Cold.
我看见女孩，我以为你们是人类
I see girl. I think you're a human.
但你猿猴们，像我一样！
But you Apes. Like me!
不，不，不要放下
No no, don't put down.
- 你在这里待了多久？     - 很长时间，很久的一段时间！
- How long have you been here?     - Long time, long long time!
家
Home.
老家
Old home.
内华达动物园
这里还有像你的猿猴吗？
Are there more like you?
- 由动物园来的更多猿猴？     - 死了，全都死了！
- More Apes from Zoo?     - Dead, all dead!
很久以前，人类患病了
Long time, human get sick
猿猴变得聪明
Apes get smart.
之后人类杀光了猿猴，但不包括我
Then human killed Apes, but not me.
我逃跑了
I run.
你如何学会说话？
You learn to speak?
听人类说话学的
Listened human.
坏猿猴
Bad Ape!
Bad Ape.
不
No
不许动
No touch.
这是我的
This is mine.
我没事
I am okay.
很惊喜...
Amazing...
总是认为我们族群是独有的
Always thought we were the only ones.
奇迹地这世上原来还有更多
Wonder if there are more in the world?
更多猿猴像我们一样
More Apes like us.
吃，吃吧
Eat. Eat.
新朋友们
New friends.
特别的日子
Special day.
加利福尼亚州，隔离检疫设施
这东西从哪里得来？
Where did you get this?
一个坏地方
Bad place
在我抵达动物园很久以前就找到了
I found it long ago after zoo.
我在寻找食物，结果找到人类动物园
I look for food, I found human zoo.
收留病患的动物园？
Zoo for sick?
巨大的围墙！ 患病的人类... 爬着
Big walls! Sick human... climb
坏人类被杀
Bad human killed.
之后，所有人患病了，所有人都死了。 以前，很久以前
And then, all get sick. All dead. For a long time, long time.
坏人类？
Bad humans?
士兵？
Soldiers?
士兵
Soldiers.
一个逃兵集中营！
A deserted military camp!
就在边境里！
On the border!
或许上校与他的军队就是往哪里去了
Maybe the Colonel and the troops are going there?
- 它远吗？ 你能带我们去吗？     - 人类动物园？
- Is it far? Can you take us?     - Human zoo?
不！  不，不可以回去那里，我...
No!  No, no go back there. I...
所有人死掉我才来这里，这里安全！
Every one dead. I came here. It's safe here!
- 永不回去！     - 求你了，你必须带我们去
- Never go back!     - Please. You must take us.
不要！不要！ 不不不！
No!   No!  No, no no
我怎可以带你去！ 怎可以带你去！ 不，不可！
How can I take! How can I take! No no!
不！ 看 看 看 看！
No! Look, look look look!
好多雪！ 我怎可以去，定要留下来！
More snow! How can I go, must stay!
你可进食，你可休息，可留下陪我
You eat, you rest, stay here with me.
这里，你的礼物
Here. You gift.
她的礼物
She gift
谁是
Who is...
孩子？
Child?
我不知道
I do not know.
但...她与你一起
But... she with you?
这里已没有其它人了
There is no one else.
我看见你现在正注视着她
I see you're looking at her just now.
你看似伤感
You look sad.
你有没有孩子？
Do you have a child?
一个
One.
另一个被人类杀了
Another was killed by human.
士兵干的？
Soldier?
我...
I...
有一个孩子
had a child.
你认为你会找到他吗？
You think you will find him?
在人类动物园内
at human zoo.
士兵
Soldier?
我不知道
I do not know.
或许吧
Maybe.
之后
Then
或许我带你去
Maybe I'll take you.
口渴
Thirsty.
路加，来吧。 走近一点
Luca, come on. Let's get closer.
保护他们安全
Keep them save
他们在干什么？
What are they doing?
我不知道
I do not know.
那是什么？ 巡逻队？
What's that? A Patrol?
我看不见策骑者
I do not see riders.
不要动！
Hold it!
我看见他们过来！
I saw them coming!
至少这一次...
At least this time...
我能够保护你
I was able to protect you.
凯撒
Caesar...
这必须停止
This must stop.
让其它猿猴参与进来还不算太迟
It's not too late to join other Apes...
我们已不能回头了！
We cannot turn back!
路加献出了自己的生命！
Luca gave his life!
求你了！
Please!
他们必须付出代价
They must pay.
现在...
Now...
你的语气就像高巴
You sound like Koba.
带你们一起来是一个错误
It was a mistake to bring you all.
这是我的战斗
This is my fight.
我会完成所有事情
I'll finish this all.
去吧，现在
Go. Now.
去加入其它猿猴群
Join the others.
发生了什么事？
What happened?
他们不知从那里走出来
They came out of nowhere...
攻击我们
Attacked us.
我们皆以为他们会将我们全体杀了
We thought they would kill us all...
但上校阻止了他们
But the Colonel stopped them!
他眼中有点疯狂！
There was madness in his eyes!
他说他们可在我们死前加以利用！
He said they would use us, before we died!
之后他们把我们都带到这里来！
And they brought us all here!
你慢慢说
You easy
他们强迫我们工作！
They've been forcing us to work!
什么样的工作？
What kind of work?
等等！ 我的小儿子也在这里吗？
Wait! My little son is here?
格林姆
Grame
和 纳里
And Nali
威灵顿
Wellington
和 拿破仑
And Napoleon
卡斯托
Castor
和 锡廷伯恩
And Sittingbourne.
你可能没有多大的放心
You probably not much relieve
但这是个伟大时刻
but this is a big moment.
你在那里？
Where were you?
我们来到你的牧群中，你非常幸运
we came upon your herd. You got lucky.
但我非常惊讶你没与他们为伍
But I am surprised you weren't with them.
我希望你不要带着遗憾地到来拯救他的生命
I hope you don't come with regret to sparing his life.
这枪射得非常好
It's quiet a good shot.
你最终有否救出你的猿猴？
Have you finally come to save your Apes?
我为你而来
I came for you.
为我？
For me?
那晚我杀了的是谁？
Who did I killed that night?
我的妻子
My wife.
我的儿子
My son.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
本来去那里是找你
I was there for you.
我的天
My God.
看看你的眼睛
Look at your eyes.
差不多成了人类
Almost human.
- 你怎知道我在这里？     - 别人告知你到这里来
- How did you know I was here?     - I was told you are coming
更多士兵由北方到来
More soldiers from the north.
- 将会与你在此会合     - 与我会合？
- Would be joining you here.     - Joining me?
将我们全体收拾掉
To finish us all
永久地
For good
谁告诉你的？
Who told you that?
好了
Okay
走吧
Let's go.
父亲！
Father!
力克
Lake.
原谅他们
Forgive them
我们经历了不少
We've been through much.
父亲！
Father!
我干了什么？
What did I done?
营队，停步！
Battalion, Halt!
- 血     - 能使草生长！
- Blood!     - Make grass grow!
- 我们！     - 让血流动！
- We!     - Make blood flow!
- 我们是个开始！     - 战斗到底！
- We are the beginning!     - At the end!
我们到这里后得不到水及食物
We haven't had food or water since we got here...
为何他们需要围墙？
Why do they need a wall?
唏...
Hey...
唏唏唏唏...
Hey hey hey hey...
唏... 猩猩！
Hey... Donkey!
- 抬走他     - 知道
- Get him!     - Okay.
好了
Okay
停手！
Leave him!
- 告诉他们让这里恢复工作     - 猿猴们需要食物和食水
- Tell them made it back to work.     - Apes need food and water.
- 告诉他们     - 给他们食物和食水
- Tell them.     - Give them food and water.
五
Five
四
Four
三
Three
二
Two
快！ 回去工作！
Hurry! Back to work!
把他绑起来，猩猩
String him up, donkey.
坏地方
Bad place
很坏的地方
Bad, bad place.
你看到什么？
What you see?
一定要救他们！
Must save them!
但怎样救？
But how?
要想想！
Must think!
凯撒会怎样干？
What would Caesar do?
噢，不好！
Oh No!
为何这么小？
Why so small?
为何上校答允你？
What did the Colonel promised you?
你真的认为他会在我们死后放过你？
You really think he let you live after we are gone?
你让他们叫你“猩猩”
You let them call you "Donkey".
你是猿猴族人
You are Ape.
上校想要见你
Colonel wants to see you.
历史
若再次阻扰工作进程，我会开始一个接一个地屠杀猿猴
Interfere with the work again, I began slaughter at the Apes one by one.
明白吗？ 我需要那围墙
Understand? I need that wall.
猿猴需要食物和食水
Apes need food and water.
当他们完成工作后才有食物和食水
They'll get food and water when they finish their work.
给猿猴食物和食水
Give Apes food and water.
- 否则他们不能完成工作     - 你知吗，你太情绪化了
- or they cannot finish it.     - You know, you're very emotional.
有何事让你认为，你有提出要求的资格？
What makes you think you are in position to make demands?
- 好吧，开始     - 士兵往这里来了
- Okay, let's go.     - The soldiers were coming here.
他们不是为了加入你们而来，是吗？
They're not coming to joining you, are they?
我看到围墙外有很多人为战争准备着
I've saw men outside on the wall preparing for battle.
他们告诉我你非常聪明，看来真的令我印象深刻
They told me you're smart, but that's impressive.
是的，他们并不是加入我方
No, they won't be joining me.
他们反抗你吗？
They are against you?
他们害怕我
They fear me.
为什么？ 因为你屠杀了你的手下？
Why? Because you kill your own men?
我们发现很多尸体
We found bodies.
这些死人都有点问题
Something wrong with these men.
天主上帝，你真有感染力
Jesus Christ, you are impressive.
你绘了一幅大图画。 你是这样看我的？！
You paint quiet a picture. What you must think of me ?!
我认为你没一点恻隐之心
I think you have no mercy.
你来这里是为了杀我
You came here to kill me.
你要展示给我看什么是恻隐之心？
Were you gonna show me mercy?
我放过你的手下时，就展示了恻隐之心
I showed you mery when I spare your men.
我给你和平的机会，而你却杀了我的家人
I offered you peace, and you killed my family.
仁慈
Mercy.
你是否真的明白对我们施与仁慈的真正意义？
Do you have any idea what you mercy would do to us?
你定是比我们坚强
You're must stronger than we are.
聪明得如此
Smart as hell.
不论你如何说，最终你做出了中止自然规律的行为
No matter what you say. Eventually, you play suspended the law of nature.
铁证在前，我们创造了你
The irony is, we created you.
你试图蔑视大自然，屈服于我们的意愿之外
You tried to defy nature, bend it to our will.
大自然为了我们如此的傲慢而惩罚了我们
And nature has been punishing us for our arrogance ever since.
十个月前，我派出侦察队去搜索你的基地
Ten months ago, I sent out recon units to look for your base.
我的亲儿子是侦察队中的一名士兵
My own son was a soldier with one of the units.
有一天他突然不再说话
One day he suddenly stopped speaking.
他变成了原始人，像一头动物
He became a primitive, like an animal.
他们与我联络，说他们认为我儿子失了心智
They contact with me, and said that they though he lost his mind,
这场战争让他承受太多了
The war is too much for him.
之后带领我儿子的士兵也同样不再说话了
Then the man who carried for him stopped speaking too.
军医在停止说话前提出了一个理论
The medic had a theory, before he stopped speaking,
出现了一种病毒几乎扫清了我们
that the virus that almost wiped us out,
每个人类幸存者依然携带着病毒
The virus that every human survivor still carries,
情况突然转变，病毒异变了！
Had suddenly changed, mutant!
如果异变了的病毒蔓延开去，这次将永久性地摧毁人类族群
And if it is spread, it would destroy humanity for good this time.
不是为了杀戮我们，而是为了掠夺我们人类、
Not by killing us, but by robbing us of those things that make us human.
我们的语言、我们高阶的思维，将我们变成一头怪物！
Our speech, our higher thinking. It would turn us into beasts!
你跟我谈仁慈吗？
You talk about mercy?
你会怎么干？
What would you have done?
就是这个时刻让我清省了
It was a moment of clarity for me.
我明白到我将要牺牲我唯一的儿子
I realized that I would have to sacrifice my only son,
来拯救人类族群
so that humanlity could be saved.
我拿着枪在手良久
I held that gun in my hand for a long time...
最终把枪指向我唯一的儿子
I pointed it at my only child.
他双眼里带着信任凝望着我
He looked me with trust in his eyes.
甚至在他原始的目光里
Even in his primitive gaze,
我感觉到他的...
I felt his...
爱
Love.
我扣下枪板
I pulled the trigger.
它净化了我
It purify me.
这使我的目标更为明确
It made my purpose clear.
我下达了命令去杀尽所有已受感染的人
I gave the order to kill the others infected, all of them.
烧光他们的随身物品及会引致污染扩散的所有东西
Burn their belongings, and anything that might spread contamination.
他们中一些人质疑我的判断
Some of the men questioned my judgement.
我问他们能否依样葫芦地跟我干同样的事
I was asking them to do what I had done,
牺牲他们的朋友及他们的家庭
To sacrifice their friends, their family.
当然地，他们拒绝了！
Of course, they refused.
因此我把他们也杀了
So I had them killed too.
其它人带着孩子们逃往丛林去
Others with children deserted into the woods.
当中有一位懦夫竟跑到我北方上司那里
One of those cowards fled to my superiors up north.
他们想说服我，说这疫症是有药可治
They tried to convince me that this plague could be dealt with medically.
之后我才真正认识到，他们根本没从过去中汲取教训
Then I realized that they had learn nothing from our past.
你也把他们杀掉？
You killed them too?
我干了什么，牧师？
What did I do, Preacher?
你劈下了他们的脑袋，长官
You severed their head, sir.
除了一个，我放过了他
Except for the one I spared
好让他能回去传递一个讯息
so that he could return to delivery a message.
如果他们想解除我的命令
If they want to relieve me of my commands
他们将要与我在此见面，由他们自己来干
They'll have to meet me here, do it themselves.
以前这里是个武器库
This used to be a weapons' depot.
当危机开始发生时，他们把这里改为一个重置营
They turn it into a relocation camp when the crisis was just beginning.
那些武器仍然保存在这里的山中
But the weapon are all still here, inside the mountain.
有多少人将会到来？
How many men will be coming?
可能是全数人
Probably all of them.
但不要想歪了
But don't get any idea,
他们唯一恐惧的东西不是我，而是你们猿猴
the only thing they fear more than me is you Apes.
这就是一场圣战
This is a holy war.
所有人类历史都导引至此刻
All the human history led to this moment.
如果我们失败，我们将是种族里的最后一群
If we lose, we'll be the last of our kind.
这将变成猿猴星球，而我们将变成你们的牲口
It will be a planet of Apes, and we'll become your cattle.
看看你
Look at you.
你认为我很病态了，是吗？
You think I am sick, don't you?
我不是存心要杀害你的儿子
I didn't mean to kill your son.
但如果他的命运是为了继承你那不神圣的王国
But if his destiny was to inherit your unholy kingdom.
我喜欢这样
I like this.
拖他出去，快出去！
Get out, come on get out!
那么情绪化！
So emotional!
我看到你有多么的矛盾
I see how conflicted you are.
你对你的目标感到困惑
You are confused in your purpose.
因我干了一些战争行为的事，而令你感到非常愤怒
You are angry at me for something I did that was an act of war.
但你对这事的处理太个人化了
But you're taking this all much far too personally.
你认为我的手下会如何处置你们猿猴？
What do you think my men would have done to your Apes,
如果你杀了我？
If you killed me?
或许还是杀了我才最重要吧？
Or still killing me is more important?
四处都是士兵！
Soldiers everywhere!
我们如何进去？
How will we get in?
一定有方法进去
Must get in somehow.
一定要进去！
Must get in!
入去
Go in?
不
No!
不要入去！ 不可以！
No go in! Not!
朋友！ 朋友！ 不可以！ 不要入去！
Friends! Friends! Not! No go in!
不要去，不要入去！
No go, no go in!
朋友！ 朋友！
Friend! Friend!
多谢，多谢朋友们
Thank you. Thank you, friends.
你拯救了我们的生命！
You save our lives!
患病的人类
Sick humans...
一定是在这里逃脱的！
...must have escaped down here!
不，不！ 不可攀爬！ 不可！
No, no! No climb! No!
什么？ 你看见什么？
What? What do you see?
究竟我们在哪里？
Wonder where we are?
噢，不要！ 我的朋友
Oh, no! Friend...
不！
No!
不！ 不要！
No! Not!
不！ 快回来，回来！
No! Come come!
快回来，回来！ 回来，回来！
Come on, come! Come come!
不！ 快回来！
No! Come on!
回来，回来！ 回来，回来！
Come come! Come come!
高巴
Koba.
睡吧
Sleep.
你救不了他们
You cannot save them.
所有猿猴都死在这里
Apes all die here.
- 不可！     - 是的！
- No!     - Yes!
加入我吧
Join me...
如果明早他还活着
If he's still alive in the morning.
他也要像其它猿猴一样回去工作
He goes back to work like everyone else.
否则射杀他
either shoot him.
来，来，来
Come. Come. Come.
小女孩入去了！
She go in!
口渴吗？
Thirsty?
躲起来，你快点
Hide. Hurry you.
人类会杀了她！
Humans will kill her!
我知要干什么！ 走吧！
I know what to do! Go!
外面还有其它猿猴吗？
Are there others out there?
清理整片区域
Sweep the area.
把牠关进去
Put him in the pen.
感觉好些了吗？
Feel better?
好些了
Good.
这样我们可谈谈关于...
Then we can talk about...
逃走之事
Escape
猿猴们团结就会强大！
Apes together strong!
- 我们是个开始！     - 战斗到底！
- We are the beginning!     - And the end!
仍活着
Still alive.
单独送他到采石场
Send him to the quarry alone.
等等
Hold on
这是什么？
What is this?
这东西怎样进来？
How did this get in there?
带他去工作
Get him to work.
三十七
Thirty-seven.
五十五
Fifty five.
三十七步到成人牢笼
Thirty-seven steps to the adult cage...
五十五步到幼儿牢笼
Fifty-five to the children.
你知吗，当围墙建成后上校会射杀所有猿猴
You know, Colonel shoot Apes when wall is done.
这围墙太疯狂了
This wall is madness.
救不了他
It won't save him.
我可干什么事能拯救你
Anymore that I did to save you.
我会拯救自己
I save of myself.
这里可有东西要你去拯救的吗？
Is there anything left...left you to save?
往上！
Up!
猿猴们是否返回牢笼中？
Apes going back to the cage?
妳...
You...
非常勇敢
Are very brave.
勇敢？
Brave?
勇敢！
Brave!
猿猴？
Ape?
我...？
Me...?
猿猴？
Ape?
妳是...
You are...
诺娃
Nova.
来，来，来看看！
Come, Come, Come to see!
来看看！
Come to see!
来！ 来看看！
Come ! Come to see!
三十四、三十五、三十六、三十七！三十！三十七！
34, 35, 36, 37! 30! 37!
我干的
I do it.
现在如何？
What now?
什么？
What?
噢，不要！
Oh, No!
不，不！不不不！
No, no! No, no, no!
好了
Okay.
这猿猴就是我给你谈论过的那只！
This is the apes I told you about!
谢谢你
Thank you.
坏猿猴
Bad Ape.
有何不妥？
What's wrong?
我们不能继续掘了！
We can't keep digging!
再掘水会灌满整条隧道！
It will flood the whole tunnel!
如不掘下去，我们则不能到达幼儿牢笼那边！
If we don't, we can't reach the children!
我们必须在下面继续看看
We must keep looking down there...
以便找出另一方法能到达幼儿牢笼
Find another way to reach the children...
我们现在必须离开！
We must leave now!
更多的士兵正来着！
More soldiers are coming!
人类会互相残杀！
Humans will destroy each other!
连我们也不放过！
And us with them!
我们将带幼儿们逃出地面去！
We'll have to get the children out above the ground!
有何方法？
How?
唏...你们这些畜牲！
Hey...You animals!
是谁干的？
Who did that?
究竟是谁？
Who was it?
是你吗？
is you?
我爱你，儿子
I love you, son.
来吧，来吧
Come on, come on.
赶快！ 走吧！
Hurry! Let's go!
凯撒，有何不妥？
Caesar, what's wrong?
赶快！ 你必须走！
Hurry! You must go!
没有你吗？
Without you?
不了
No.
莫利斯是对的
Morris was right.
我干这些似足高巴
I did that like Koba.
他逃不出他的仇恨
He could not escape his hate.
可惜我仍不能逃避我自己
And I still can not escape mine.
快走！ 走，走，走，走，走，走！
Move! Go, go, go, go, go, go!
上校！ 上校！
Colonel! Colonel!
他跑到哪里去了？
Whare the hell is he?
上校，你在吗？
Colonel, Are you in there?
上校？
Colonel?
猩猩！ 榴弹发射器！
Donkey! Grenade launcher!
老天该死的猩猩！ 快给我发射器！
God damn it, donkey! Get me the launcher!
噢，不要！不，不，不！
Oh, No! No, no, no!
不用担心
Don't worry
莫利斯
Morris
你现在已在家园了
You are on home now
猿猴全族都很强大...
Apes all strong...
就算有没有我也一样
with or without me
子孙们将会知道谁是众人之父，与及凯撒为我们所付出的一切
Son will know who was father and what Caesar did for us.
凯撒
Caesar